<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of certaine things in Spaine worthy of obseruation: Set forth by Stephen Man, one of the yeomen of his Maiesties chamber.</title>
            <author>Man, Stephen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06803)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 812:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of certaine things in Spaine worthy of obseruation: Set forth by Stephen Man, one of the yeomen of his Maiesties chamber.</title>
                  <author>Man, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Im]printed [by T. Snodham] for Iohn Browne, a[nd are] to be sold in S. Dunstanes church-[yard ..] in Fleetstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 227) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page mutilated, with some loss of print; lacks all after page 30 (perfect copy has 161 [9] pages).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  Court and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2707:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF CERTAINE things in SPAINE, worthy <hi>of Obſeruation:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth by STEPHEN MAN, one of the Yeomen of his <hi>Maieſties Chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>GOD IS MY HELPER</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mprinted for <hi>Iohn Browne,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be ſold in <hi>S. Dunstanes</hi> Church-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Fleetſtreete, 161<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2707:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2707:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable, <hi>George,</hi> Marquiſſe, and Earle of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> vicount VILLIERS, Barron <hi>of</hi> Whaddon, <hi>Lord high Admirall of</hi> England, Iuſtice in Eyre of al his Ma<hi rend="sup">ies</hi>. Forreſts, Parkes, and Chaſes beyond <hi>Trent,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ies</hi>. horſe, Knight</hi> of the moſt noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maieſties moſt honourable priuie Counſell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince your Lo. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are ſuch, as they haue a Title to all mens labours, both by your honourable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation and fauour, as your value, and iudgement of them: It is an honeſt ambition of my humbleneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2707:3"/>
to adde ſomething to the heape is dayly offered to your altar, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that nothing is brought thither with ſincerer hands then this ſmall gift of mine owne collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Spaine: which if they retayne but a good odour in your receiuing, and that your Honour will take the minde wherewith they are done, it will be a grace, that ſhall euer ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my induſtry, to the ſtudy of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and honouring your Lordſhip, in the name of your Lordſhip</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>moſt bounden, <hi>Stephen Man.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2707:3"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF CERTAINE Things in SPAINE, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of obſeruation.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Orders Militarie and their Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes and Reuenewes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here belongeth to the Order of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> 94. Knighthoods, and all yeeld yearely 3280312 Duckates.</p>
               <p>The Knights of this Order, weare a croſſe of Scarlet or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Veluet, or one of Gold hung in a chaine: they haue for their patron S. <hi>Iames,</hi> and their rule hath beene drawne from S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2707:4"/>The order of <hi>Calatraua</hi> hath 50. Knighthoods, and all yeeld yeerely 1300634. Duckats.</p>
               <p>They follow the rule of S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and weare a ſcarlet Croſſe, or crimſon veluet, or a <hi>Venero</hi> of Gold.</p>
               <p>That of <hi>Alcantara</hi> hath 58. Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and all yeeld yeerely, 1120269. Duckats.</p>
               <p>They follow the rule of S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and weare a Croſſe of the making of that of <hi>Calatraua,</hi> although it be greene; and of all theſe Orders and of thoſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Monteſa,</hi> his Maieſty is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall adminiſtrator.</p>
               <p>There belongeth to that of <hi>Monteſa Origmaria de Valencia</hi> thirteene knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and yeeld yearely, 230. Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kates.</p>
               <p>The Croſſe of this order is of Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, or Veluet, they follow the rule of S. <hi>Bennet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That of Chriſt is of Portingale, and the Croſſe is of colour, and a white ſtreake in the mideſt of it. His Maieſty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2707:4"/>
giues the Knighthoods, and ſome the Duke of <hi>Braganca;</hi> the number of the Knighthoodes are not knowne, nor what they are worth.</p>
               <p>To the order of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> although it is not in <hi>Spaine,</hi> belongeth 129. Knighthoodes, beſides <hi>los Prioratos,</hi> and they yeeld in all yearly, 9110250. Duckats.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Grandes, there is no preheminence but onely of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Conſtable, the others ſeate themſelues in the publicke Acts, as it happeneth, without any ſuperiority.</p>
               <p>The Admirall of <hi>Caſtille</hi> may enter into the Councell with his Cloake and Rapier, and ſeate himſelfe at the left hand of the Preſident of <hi>Caſtille at</hi> all times when he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Medina Celi</hi> euery yeare on Twelfe day deliuereth a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall vnto his Maieſty, clayming the Kingdome of <hi>Caſtille</hi> as heire of <hi>Henrig</hi> and the other Kings; which is remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Royall Councell, and there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2707:5"/>
is neuer made any more diſpute of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſcay</hi> is excepted; when the King enters there, he is to haue one leg vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</p>
               <p>It is not permitted to proceede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of the Grandes, nor their firſt begotten, without expreſſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the King in writing; to whom when as any ſuch thing happeneth, they put in ſureties, and in the meane time there comes order from the King what ſhall be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Knights of the golden fleece which are in Spaine.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>HIs Maieſty.</item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Alua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Oſſuna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Arios.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Medina Celi.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Eſcalona.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Cardoua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke de <hi>Montalto.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Earle de <hi>Oropeſa.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Marquiſſe <hi>Eſpinola.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2707:5"/>
               <head>Charges which his Maiesty is at.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe vice Roy of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The vice Roy of <hi>Portingale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The vice Roy of <hi>Nauarre.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The vice Roy of <hi>Valencia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The vice Roy of <hi>Cerdena.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The vice Roy of <hi>Sicilia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The gouernour of <hi>Milan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The chiefe Generall of the Sea.</item>
                  <item>The Generall of the Gallies of Spaine.</item>
                  <item>The Generall of <hi>Sicilia:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of <hi>Genoua:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of <hi>Portingale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter Generall of the field of Spaine.</item>
                  <item>Mr. General of the field of Portingale.</item>
                  <item>Generall of the <hi>Caualleria</hi> of Spaine.</item>
                  <item>Generall of the Caualleria of <hi>Milan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vice Roy of <hi>Peru.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vice Roy of <hi>Mexico.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vice Roy of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vice Roy of <hi>Mallorca.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gouernour of <hi>Galicia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vice Roy of <hi>Cataluna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2707:6"/>Gouernour of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gouernour of <hi>Oran.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. Generall of the field of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Generall of the <hi>Caualleria</hi> of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Generall of the Artillery of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>General of the Armada of the Ocea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſea.</item>
                  <item>The Royall Admirall thereof.</item>
                  <item>Generall of the Gallies of the Plate.</item>
                  <item>Generall of the Fleete.</item>
                  <item>The Admirall thereof.</item>
                  <item>The Embaſſador of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Embaſſadour in <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Embaſſadour in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Embaſſadour in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Embaſſadour in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Embaſſadors in the <hi>Signories:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Venice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Sauoy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Genoua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Florence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Ferrara.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Parma.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Mantua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Luca.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In <hi>Vrbina.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2707:6"/>
               <head>Men and women ſeruants belonging to the Queene.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Lady of the Chamber;</item>
                  <item>twenty Ladies, and their ſeruants.</item>
                  <item>The Nurſe of the Prince and Infants, eight Chamber-maides.</item>
                  <item>Fiue maiſters of the Princes.</item>
                  <item>The Landres of the Kings body.</item>
                  <item>Landres for the Princes.</item>
                  <item>Two guardians of the reſt of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</item>
                  <item>Sixe Ladies of honour.</item>
                  <item>Foure Aſſiſtants of the Chamber.</item>
                  <item>The Landres of Eſtate.</item>
                  <item>The Miſtriſſe of the worke.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Keeper of the Iewels, two inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>Foure maides of Eſtate belonging to the Ladies.</item>
                  <item>The high Chamberlaine.</item>
                  <item>Fiue Chamberlaines more, twelue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ones.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe book-keeper of the wages.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2707:7"/>Foure aſſiſtants.</item>
                  <item>One Secretary.</item>
                  <item>One Treaſurer.</item>
                  <item>One Secretary of the Chamber.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe houſe-keeper.</item>
                  <item>Foure Aſſiſtants.</item>
                  <item>Two Phyſitions of the Chamber.</item>
                  <item>Sixe of the Family.</item>
                  <item>One Chirurgion.</item>
                  <item>Six gentlemen of the Society.</item>
                  <item>Eleauen Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>Twelue keepers of the Ladies.</item>
                  <item>One that keepeth the ſick Ladies.</item>
                  <item>Foure doore-keepers of the Ladies.</item>
                  <item>Foure meſſengers.</item>
                  <item>The ſuperiour and inferiour Tapeſtry keepers.</item>
                  <item>The Maſter of the hall of the Ladies.</item>
                  <item>The dauncing Maſter.</item>
                  <item>Foure keepers of the Plate.</item>
                  <item>Eight Chamberlaines.</item>
                  <item>One Booke-keeper.</item>
                  <item>The Maſter of the Muſicke.</item>
                  <item>Of all the Artiſts of the Court there is one belongeth to the Queene, and hangeth her Armes in his ſhop.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2707:7"/>
               <head>The Queenes Kitchin.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>ONe Steward.</item>
                  <item>Two Ouerſeers.</item>
                  <item>One Ouerſeer of the maide ſeruants.</item>
                  <item>A Caruer.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Cooke.</item>
                  <item>Foure officers of the Kitchin.</item>
                  <item>Foure Water-bearers.</item>
                  <item>Six porters of the Kitchin.</item>
                  <item>One buttler of the bread.</item>
                  <item>Another of the victuals.</item>
                  <item>Another of the Kings bread.</item>
                  <item>Another for the vulgar.</item>
                  <item>A Diſpenſer.</item>
                  <item>The Paſtie-maker.</item>
                  <item>A Clearke of the fruit and wood.</item>
                  <item>The broth-maker.</item>
                  <item>The ſauce-maker.</item>
                  <item>Two ſeruants to aſſiſt the ſauce-maker.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2707:8"/>
               <head>Cauallaerica of the Queene.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Maſter of the Horſe.</item>
                  <item>His Lieutenant.</item>
                  <item>One Ouerſeer.</item>
                  <item>A Secretary.</item>
                  <item>Foure Furrieles.</item>
                  <item>Three Horſe-curers.</item>
                  <item>Thirteene Lacquaies.</item>
                  <item>22. of thoſe that prouide Mules when the King remoues.</item>
                  <item>20. ſeruants of the Caualleria.</item>
                  <item>Tenne Coachmen.</item>
                  <item>Ten ſeruants belonging to the Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Queenes priuate Chappell.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe Confeſſor.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Almnor.</item>
                  <item>Two aſſiſtants.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Taper-keeper.</item>
                  <item>Two inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>One that keepes the Hoſte.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2707:8"/>Two yong men of the Oratory.</item>
                  <item>Here the Kings Chaplins ſay Maſſe when they are nominated, and doe it by turnes.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſeruice and ſeruants of the King.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe high Chamberlaine.</item>
                  <item>Fiue inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>Gentlemen of his Chamber, with a gilded key, of no certaine number.</item>
                  <item>Gentlemen of the Kings dyet.</item>
                  <item>Gentlemen of the houſe.</item>
                  <item>Secretary and keeper of the writings of his Maieſty.</item>
                  <item>24. Pages more or leſſe with their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Tutor.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe booke-keeper of the wages.</item>
                  <item>A Treaſurer.</item>
                  <item>A Paymaſter.</item>
                  <item>The high Poſte-maſter.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Harbenger. 3. inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe keeper of the Iewels.</item>
                  <item>Ten Iewell keepers more.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2707:9"/>Two Phyſitions belonging to the Chamber.</item>
                  <item>Eight belonging to the houſe.</item>
                  <item>The keeper of the bookes.</item>
                  <item>Foure of the Royall houſe.</item>
                  <item>Tenne continuall ones.</item>
                  <item>Fifty <hi>Monteros</hi> of <hi>Eſpinola,</hi> which are Guardiens of the Chamber.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Tapeſtry Maſter and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ones.</item>
                  <item>Sixe Chamberlaines of the beds.</item>
                  <item>Sixe aſſiſtants and inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>Eight Porters.</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Waterman &amp; his inferiors.</item>
                  <item>Foure Horſe Riders,</item>
                  <item>The chiefe Snuffer of the Candles.</item>
                  <item>Sixe inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>Of all the Artiſts of the Court, there is one of the King, and placeth the Kings Armes in his ſhop.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kings Guard.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>A 100. archers, borgons &amp; fle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mings,</item>
                  <item>100. Spaniſh Halberdiers.</item>
                  <item>100. Halberdiers of Switſers.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2707:9"/>The olde Guard being Horſemen, are 50. Spaniards.</item>
                  <item>The olde Foote-guard are 50. or more.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Armory of the King.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Armorer.</item>
                  <item>Ten Officers of the Armory.</item>
                  <item>Ten inferiour ones.</item>
                  <item>Sixe ſeruants which clenſe the pouder.</item>
                  <item>Foure Porters of the Armory.</item>
                  <item>Foure Kings of Armes.</item>
                  <item>24. Trumpetters.</item>
                  <item>Eight Drummers, 16. inferiour ones.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſeruice of the Kings dyet.</head>
               <p>THe Gentlemen of the Chamber, ſerue his Maieſties Table by turnes, as the Ladies doe the Queenes; and hath once againe ſo many ſeruices of meate as the Queene hath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Offices belonging to the Huntſmen.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Huntſman.</item>
                  <item>Sixe more.</item>
                  <item>10. Maſters of the Croſſe-bowes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2707:10"/>Eight Huntſmen more.</item>
                  <item>10. a horſebacke.</item>
                  <item>The Seruants of the Hounds.</item>
                  <item>4. Huntſmen of the wilde Chaſe.</item>
                  <item>13. Hare-hunters.</item>
                  <item>14. a horſebacke with euery one his Gray hound.</item>
                  <item>12. that winde the horne.</item>
                  <item>Foure Huntſmen of the Bull.</item>
                  <item>Sixe keepers of the Nets and Engins belonging to the hunting.</item>
                  <item>4 Aſſiſtants.</item>
                  <item>4. Keepers of the Hounds.</item>
                  <item>All theſe, beſides the Horſemen which ſerue his Maieſty, are together a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back when the King rideth a hunting.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Officers of the Cauallerica.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Maſter of the Horſe.</item>
                  <item>His Lieuetenant.</item>
                  <item>4. Equall with him.</item>
                  <item>8. Groomes of the Stable.</item>
                  <item>A booke-keeper.</item>
                  <item>Two ouerſeers.</item>
                  <item>10. Ryders.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2707:10"/>24. Lacquies.</item>
                  <item>6. Horſe-curers.</item>
                  <item>4. Coachmen of his Maieſty.</item>
                  <item>20. Coachmen for the Commons.</item>
                  <item>20. Prouiders of the Mules when the King remoues.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Chappell Royall.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe chiefe Chaplin.</item>
                  <item>His Maieſties Confeſſor.</item>
                  <item>The Chaplins of the Altar.</item>
                  <item>The Chaplins of honour, who ſit, and are couered with their Coapes.
<list>
                        <item>There is three ſorts of them, the firſt is of the houſe of <hi>Caſtille,</hi> and the King payes them: the ſecond is of the Crowne of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and the Crowne payes them: the third is of the Orders of S. <hi>Iames, Calatraua, Alcantara,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn, Chriſt, and Monteſa:</hi> and theſe are paide by the Maſters of the tables of theſe orders. All which are to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the King equall in degree.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>One Maſter of the Chappell.</item>
                  <item>60. Muſitians.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2707:11"/>A Tenent of the Mr. of the Chappell.</item>
                  <item>Two Maſters of the Ceremonies.</item>
                  <item>Two Organiſts.</item>
                  <item>Sixe children of the Oratory.</item>
                  <item>One chief Almnor, &amp; two inferior ones.</item>
                  <item>One chiefe Taper-bearer, and three</item>
                  <item>Aſſiſtants.</item>
                  <item>The Hoſte-maker.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Order of the Roiall Chappell.</head>
               <p>IN the Royall Chappell none are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnleſſe it be one of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of a King, Crowne, or Venice, and the Chaplins of Honour with their Coapes. At the right hand of the chiefe Altar there is a Bench richly couered, the face towards the body of the Church, on the which ſit the Biſhops which are preſent at the diuine ſeruice, at the foote of the Altar there is a ſeate for his Maty. and a Cuſhion for his knees and elbowes which are alwaies agreeable with the furniture of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, except the King mourne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2707:11"/>Lower without the Archof the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, there is a great Bench couered with Tapeſtry, where the Grandes ſit.</p>
               <p>At the other ſide on the left hand of the Altar, there is a ſeat for the Biſhops and chiefe Chaplin: a little lower, right ouer his Maty. there is a ſeate for the Nuncio and other Embaſſadors.</p>
               <p>Lower without the Arch, before the ſeate of the Grandes, ſtand two, one behinde the other, and vncouered, for the Chaplins.</p>
               <p>Behinde the ſeate of the Grandes and Chaplins, there ſtand vncouered all the Knights, men of renowne, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and ſeruants of the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, which goe to Maſſe to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to heare the diuine ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Betweene the curtaine of the King, and the ſeate of the Grandes, there is a ſeate appointed for the High-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine, who ſitteth couered, although he be not one of the Grandes, in that place, by reaſon of his office; &amp; behinde him ſtand two Archers of the Guard.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2707:12"/>Neere the Curtaine Royall ſtand the Maſters of the Ceremonies; theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the dignity which is found in the Church, and bring to his Maty. the Euangeliſts and the Pax to kiſſe them, and the foure Chamberlaines goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Dignity, and returne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with vnto the foote of the Altar, and then returne to their places, which is behinde the Embaſſadors, and there ſtand; and hauing no dignity, one of the Chaplins carrieth the <hi>Miſſall</hi> and the <hi>Pax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Maieſty giues way to the great Prior of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> to enter in the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Royall, and ſeateth himſelfe in a ſeate behinde his Maieſty.</p>
               <p>Before the Altar ſtand four echayres of ſtate; in the loweſt, the Queen, Prince, and Infants heare Maſſe: and this chayr or ſeate is cloſe ſhut, and ſo they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeene. In the ſecond is the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, and likewiſe there are ſome ſeates, wheron there ſit ſome Knights &amp; men of renowne, which come there to heare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2707:12"/>
the diuine Seruice; the which ſit and are couered, becauſe that is not repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Chappell, and it is lawfull for euery one to ſit and be couered.</p>
               <p>In the other two ſeates aboue, ſit the Ladies and wayting gentlewomen of the Queene and other Ladies which goe to the Chappell, and it is hard to enter by the quarter of the Queene, and there is no other entrance.</p>
               <p>On Twelfe day his Maty. offers in remembrance of the three that came from the Eaſt, three ſiluer Cups, which are giuen to three Monaſteries of poore Nunnes.</p>
               <p>The day his Maty. came to full age, hee offereth ſo much in Crownes.</p>
               <p>On holy Thurſday his Maty. waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the feete of certaine poore men, as the Pope doth at Rome, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them to be cloathed and foode to be giuen them. If the Nuncio be a Cardinall, there is a ſeate ſet for him in the Chappel Royall, as for the King; and the like for whatſoeuer Cardinall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2707:13"/>
right ouer againſt that of his Maieſty.</p>
               <p>When his Maty. goeth to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the Guard of the Spaniſh and Germaine Halberdiers are placed in ranck from the gate of the Hall of the Guard, vnto that of the Chappell. The Spaniards at the right hand, and at his returne the Germaines haue it. In the middeſt goe the <hi>Furrieles</hi> of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and then the Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which accompany him, and after them the chiefe of the houſe with their ſtaues; and then the Grandes two and two, and then the Prince of Sauoy when he is at Court, and then the King; after him the Nuncio and Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors in their orders, &amp; then the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and chiefe Chamberlaines, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them come in troupes, the Archers: if there be any Cardinall in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he goeth at the left hand of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and at the comming out, they obſerue this order.</p>
               <p>His Maty. goeth out vncouered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the middeſt of the Chappell, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2707:13"/>
there he couereth himſelfe, and walkes two ſteps, and preſently deſires the Prince his couſin that he would bee couered; and walking two paces more, returnes to the Embaſſadors, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires them to be couered; and comming to the ſhadowes of the Gates of the Church, deſires the Grandes to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner how the Kings eate in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</head>
               <p>ON the chiefe feaſt dayes, their Maties. are accuſtomed to eate in publique, as at Eaſter, and Twelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide; and the ſeruice of the Queene in publique vpon ſuch days is as followes.</p>
               <p>The Table is ſet vpon a place ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what high from the ground, richly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and at the vpper end is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of his Maieſty: and vpon the firſt napkin they put two loaues, one very big and white, &amp; the other ſomewhat browne, whereof his Maieſty moſt commonly eateth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2707:14"/>And at the bringing in of the meate, there goes before it three Corporalls of the three Guardes of the Archers, Halberdiers, Spaniards and Germanes; then the Mace-bearers with their Maces of ſiluer and gilt, with the armes of <hi>Castille</hi> and <hi>Leon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Chamberlaines with their Staues, and after them the high Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine, with his long Staffe vpon his ſhoulder; then the meaner ſort with meate, all incompaſſed with thoſe of the Guard, and the high Chamberlaine couered. And in the meane time the meate paſſeth, all thoſe which in the meane time doe paſſe, are to be vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and the Guard haue a care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe the ſame; and ſo in the place or hall where the diſhes or meates of the King ſtand or any part thereof, or the Cup wherein they drinke, not any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is to be couered, vnleſſe it be one of the Grandes or the high Chamberlaine.</p>
               <p>The meate being ſet on the Table by the high Chamberlaine, the Queene
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2707:14"/>
comes, and being ſet at Table, it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that ſome enter which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee them eate.</p>
               <p>It concernes the Ladies, three eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day by their turnes, to come and ſerue the Table; the one vncouereth the diſhes in their order, and deliuers them in the hands of the other, who deliuereth the diſh to the Queene; and her Maty. is ſilent, and deliuers the diſh to the other, and ſhe makes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a ſmall diſh for the Queen; and then ſhe deliuers the diſh in the hands of ſome of the inferiour ones, who carries the ſame away. Theſe three Ladies which ſerue, ſtand with their napkins vpon their ſhoulders, and are very gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant.</p>
               <p>One Chaplin of honour is alwaies found ready there to bleſſe the Table, and is accuſtomed to commaund the diſhes to be deliuered to the Queene.</p>
               <p>When her Maty. will not haue any ſuch diſh, then ſhe lifteth vp her head, and preſently it is ſent away; and at
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2707:15"/>
euery diſh the napkin is changed, and the number of the diſhes is from 15. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at publique meales.</p>
               <p>When her Maty. pleaſeth to drinke, ſhe makes a ſigne with her head to one of the Ladies which ſerue the Table, and there is another Lady which doth aſſiſt her to giue the meate; and then one of the foure Chamberlaines doth accompany one of the inferiour ones to the gate of the Buttery: then he who keepeth the Buttery, deliuereth to one of the meaner ſorte a ſiluer plate with a couered Cup full of water; for the Queene drinkes no Wine. Then he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the ſaid Plate; goeth to the Chamberlaine, who with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth accompany it, where the place is, where the Lady is, who is to giue her Maieſty the drinke.</p>
               <p>Then the Lady falleth downe vpon her knees at the feete of her Maty: then taketh off the couer of the Cup with two fingers of her left hand, and with the other two foremoſt ſhee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2707:15"/>
taketh the plate; and then with her right hand ſhe taketh the cup, and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the plate a little of the water, and drinketh it; &amp; then putteth the cup againe on the plate, and putting it in her right hand, with the left ſhe coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the cup againe, and taking it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the left hand, ſhee giues it to her Maty. and preſently with her right hand ſhee vncouereth the Cup: and when the Queene hath drunke, the Lady couereth the Cup in riſing vp, and hauing done her reuerence, ſhee deliuers it againe to the inferiour one.</p>
               <p>At the comming of the fruit, the Chamberlaine commeth with the ſame Company as is aforeſaid, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of one of the Ladies which ſerue the Table, and the meaner ſort bring it, &amp; giue it to one of the Ladies which put it there; in the meane time they take away the meate from the Table, and giue it to the meaner ſort, who carry it away. At the time when her Maty. eateth, the Grandes which are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2707:16"/>
preſent ſtand couered, leaning to the wall, and the Ladies which doe not ſerue that day, ſtand in the ſame peece, conferring with their Gallants; for at that time it is lawfull for them, &amp; thoſe which doe ſerue are wont to turne backe ſometimes vpon occaſions to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute their friends.</p>
               <p>In the meane time, her Maty. ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and dinner paſſeth, on ſuch daies they ſound in the yard of the Pallace with drummes and trumpets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner of the Kings eating.</head>
               <p>THe like Ceremonies are vſed when the King eateth in publique in his quarter, but onely that in ſtead of the Ladies, Gentlemen ſerue the Table e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in his turne, &amp; the ſame ſerue the meale on ſuch dayes in ſtead of the Pages, all vncouered, and with their cloake and rapier; onely the high Chamberlaine is couered by reaſon of his office. Moreouer the Kings Table
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2707:16"/>
is ſerued with the Aſſembly of the Towne houſe, and the foure Kings of Armes with their rich Coates, with the Armes of <hi>Caſtille</hi> and <hi>Leon,</hi> and the Mace bearers with their Maces of ſiluer and gilt, with the ſame Armes: there are deuided two for the King, and two for the Queene, and alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the meate with the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls and Grandes.</p>
               <p>When their Maties. eate in publique together, all this is ioyned, ordered with the ſame order without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Kings take Coach.</head>
               <p>THey aduertiſe before hand with Trumpettes, &amp; Drummes when their Maties. come forth, and preſently the horſemen make themſelues ready, and the other perſons which are to goe in the company; and their Maties. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, they bow downe, bringing the King to the Queene, accompanied
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2707:17"/>
with the Noble Men and Ladies of honour.</p>
               <p>At the entrance of the Coach, a Knight lifteth vp the boote, and the high Chamberlaine takes his Maty. by the Arme, to aſſiſt him into the coach. His Maty. comming to the boote, takes off his Bonnet, and ſaluteth the Queene, and lets her goe in firſt, and ſitteth at the right hand; then preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the King goeth in, and the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines and maſter of the horſe goe in another Coach, which goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Then the chiefe Lady of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the other Ladies go into other Coaches; and the Gentlemen which ſerue them, euery one helpeth his Lady into the Coach, and afterwards they horſe themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2707:17"/>
               <head>Ordinary charges of the Kings and Queenes houſe.</head>
               <p>FOr the Horſe-men euery moneth foure thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the furniſhing of the houſe one moneth with another, fiue hundred Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the ſhop of agreement, three thouſand Rials euery moneth.</p>
               <p>For wages yeerely, one hundreth forty and foure thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the Merchants of agreement yeerely, eighteene thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the Queriſters of the Chappell monethly, 000120. Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the keeper of the Iewels yeerely, fiue thouſand and foure hundered Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the charges of the Tapeſtry yeerely, one hundred forty and foure thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the ordinary Plate of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie yeerely, one hundred forty and foure thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2707:18"/>For the expences of the Queene, one hundred and twenty thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For ordinary Almes yeerely, are ſeauen thouſand and two hundred Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the expences of the high Poſt-Maſter yeerely, two and forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the expences of the <hi>Snora In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi> a Nunne, yeerely, three thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>To the Treaſurer of the Queene for expences of ſuch things as her Maieſtie and others eateth betweene meales, is yeerely ſixe and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the Chamber of the King yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, foure &amp; twenty thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the expences of the chiefe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen of the Queenes Chamber yeerely, ſixe thouſand Duckats.</p>
               <p>For the expences of the Prince of Spaine, yeerely, ſixe and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckats.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2707:18"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
